okay I know they're working I know I
can't see the chat oh maybe it's working
now okay cool
see you guys joining can someone try to
chat and we are back okay cool
right now for me the stream looks frozen
is that true for you too
I hope we're good so I'm trying to
actually broadcast my not frozen okay
cool
excellent alright so we can close that
out you don't need that so what we're
gonna be playing with today is I'm
sitting here in my rav4 and if I want to
see myself I gotta look over here
alright so I'm streaming for my Mac this
time you can see that I've added
something to the Panda examples repo
called query VIN you can see right here
this is the VIN number of my car what
we're going to be playing with today is
it turns out that a lot of cars don't
actually have messages being sent on the
canvas you're gonna have to send
commands to it in order to get the car
to tell you things if you look at these
obd2 pigs so you know when I talk about
every other car dongle this is what they
can get these standard PIDs close up the
window standard PID so to show you PID
supported engine load fuel pressure rpm
vehicle speed that kind of stuff so
we're gonna try to make some of those
queries today so I've written a script
called query VIN I committed it to panda
examples this morning we take a look at
what it is
it sends some stuff it's really kind of
terribly written code um so we should do
a little bit of refactoring so can you
guys we'll see if I make them that big
ice OTP is a standard on top of can that
let's it kind of packet eyes can because
can has only a eight byte limit per
message so if you want to send things
that are more than eight bytes you got
to packetize them
so first let's try something so I'm
actually setting the safety mode on the
panda remember pandas can't transmit by
default setting the safety mode to wall
output so let's see if we can instead
set the safety mode to elm isn't
documented here so we're gonna add this
we can find this in the board go get a
safety cage yeah e3 to 7 is Elm let's
just add this here also we have safety
toyotas board here better way yes make
sure my panda repose update everything
origin that's very cool already okay
cool so let's see what happens if I set
the safety mode so first of all I'll
show you guys what happens if I set the
safety mode to no out shouldn't work
yeah so it sends but it doesn't actually
send it sounds nothing so if I set the
safety mode instead to elm327 I'll try
to look up every once in a while to see
you guys on the chat still doesn't work
works if I set it to all output but only
all output when I was working I set it
out interest maybe LM isn't actually
triggering a reinitialize ation of can
read the code so if I look in main here
this is set safety mode should trigger a
cannon at all
why doesn't work so it's weird if I
toggle from no outputs or it doesn't
work then I changed elm327 it still
doesn't I don't know it works the second
time okay so the first time I just must
be clogged up with crap cool so that's
good to know
so now let's see if we can make some of
these other queries to the car the
request that I'm making for the VIN is
own I know to equals gab move in and
then I'm doing a iso TP receive so I
believe if I recall correctly 7d F is a
broadcast address and 78 is the address
I expect to hear back from the ECU on
let's see what other queries I can make
here I hope this is still visible to you
guys yeah I still read the Wikipedia I'm
just on the obd2 bids Wikipedia
yeah this will be in the Panda repo I'm
gonna push whenever I'm done um that
wasn't the can bus that was finicky I
find the campus is actually super
reliable so you see right now I'm
sending a PID 9 yeah text is hard to
read okay I can try to zoom in a little
bit more mode 9 PID 2 is the vehicle
identification number it's really
unreadable shouldn't be it's pretty
readable here oh yeah okay I can see why
that's kind of hard to read let me zoom
in a little more I'll keep it at 100
I'll make it fullscreen if I have to it
is 4 bytes what's 4 bytes so I want to
send a mode 9 that can request the VIN
message count in pit usually value will
be 5 calibration ID what's a calibration
ID so I found that cars call things I
need to start live streaming on YouTube
you have people tell me this I'm a
Twitter fanboy you know you know I love
the Twitter let's see what the ECU name
is let's see if we can request that Oh
ECM engine control cool so I'm gonna
break out my ISO teepee library a little
bit I think we can actually eventually
just make this part of Panda so this is
a 2017 rav4 so up here is kind of the
ISO TV library so let me just break that
out to ISO GP dot
so much worse at using computers when
people are watching me even anonymous
people on the Internet oh yeah cool so
now I can say from ISO TP in porch
I said TP send this computer see you
pass in the Panda as the first argument
so won't push this little library here
on so you guys will be able to do this
stuff in your car so that's got a
broadcast let's see if we can find any
other ECU's in this car
let's also just text up that red because
I don't actually think I think I'm
getting more information than what's
there yeah look I'm getting this well
that's just part of the response
interesting just what I have in response
to interesting luring it thank you
yeah it's part of the VIN response oh
I'm not you unpacking that cool I'm so
4902 Lotus and that's like a response to
my to my command ECM probably engine
control model and this is engine control
so let's see if we can get any father
easy-to-use to respond and ask them
their names like looping through some
stuff almost longer for stop signs and
traffic lights so it looks like if I
send it doesn't matter if I son to which
is broadcast or I think 750 is actually
the ECM ECU itself
my thoughts on supercruise I haven't got
to try it if anyone has it and we wants
to let me try I'll be happy to give you
my thoughts mama no we can just set the
safes I know what I'm doing my garage
it's a neighbor's garage yeah cool so I
can actually send it to that one as well
I can send it to three so let's look up
Toyota like clear my history your
history comes up still enough and uh
incognito load um how much long until
you've run out of money we're not
running out of money man oh my guy is
coming is we are gonna be more serious
about sales of our products though why
do I need to see inside what box am i
looking inside boxes I just got a chrome
preferences here and clear my history
person one edit person why do I have to
look inside OBD is it part of advanced
when I look at all this chrome stuff
clear since the beginning of time you
can say those those are fine browsing
history download history yeah it sounds
good
bye bye cool how may i I see oh yeah
funny
any upcoming open pilot updates well
that is coming very very soon zero point
three point seven and it comes with
silky smooth lateral control so I hope
you guys appreciate it it was a web
service use a prediction surface some do
not shout Wow chromis all the stuff man
well formed it we definitely only -
hosted app date I don't know dad cool no
vision only you guys with that I've
never actually met someone in your life
who has a Subaru I'm looking at my phone
I'm not looking at you that's you over
there cool yeah so silky silky lateral
not not longitudinal yeah that is uh
people are working on that right now um
so let's check out Charlie noise thing
actually has some good information
Toyota car hacking media cracking porous
and by panel you know we hope like like
I said we ordered we ordered ten
thousand pandas I hope to sell these all
next year come to Australia 50% of sugru
guess your showroom you're out think
you're our ACCC is too bad the vision is
only if the lateral only uses vision so
that might be what you want so oh
manufacturing no no we're shipping out
okay so this is the anti-lock brake ECU
it should be on 760 so let's try to send
760 see if we can get a name that looks
like something reasonable so we would
expect a response on seven six eight No
so I think you want to all-out but what
in their work
they got the he doesn't respond to a
name query so maybe they're all the
seven continents this is probably
something I should do more googling for
sending things to my car never turns out
now I should know like Python one-liners
for time outs nice just like the one I
know it works yeah that works
no that one's responded to me
Oh D responds to me as well that's
interesting
D responds with an invalid cool so to
see so it was big age is not okay so
there's something at B C and D they just
seem like they don't have names look I
could write like I've given you guys the
deal with the vision only ACC before if
somebody shows me that they have a car
that they can control then I will
happily spend some time and fix it for
you it already kind of works too I don't
know if anyone's actually tried it yeah
if you comment up the other radar it'll
work okay cool so it looks like I'm
actually getting responses from these
ECU's what's ever on B 0 C 0 and D 0
they're just not so what I'm trying to
do right now is two things first off I
have to add Elm support to a not male
but like ad standard PID support to
shiver um the other thing I have to do
is figure out how to knock out the
driving support ECU in the Toyotas so
the driving support ECU is what's
responsible for the onboard fairly low
quality adaptive cruise control we want
to knock it out and we wanna replace it
with comet adaptive cruise control
because it's way better so for the
lateral we can actually just unplug the
the camera module the driving support
ECU is hidden much deeper in the car and
we want to keep our brand-new rav4 as
pristine as possible so we're gonna try
to do it with software now realistically
probably the right idea here is for me
to get the Toyota text stream software
hey do I want Japanese food that's kind
of tempting but then I gotta switch off
periscope um yes oppa violet can already
do vision uh yeah yeah I could go for
some Japanese yeah she ball sounds good
I don't know if you're watching I don't
have slack I can't get to slack it's on
my phone if I switch off of periscope
periscope man Josh Andy I got your
Aussie ball alright I give that up 50%
heads working so you can't just comment
out radar D it's gonna take a bit more
effort than that no no no we have an
internal slack but we need more
computers no we need that we walk the
talkies right I need more phone so have
another phone right here let me you know
what I'll send him an email
I know his email I'll send him an email
from this phone okay I got a phone yeah
sure she ball please okay so now I think
my odds are getting across your bowl get
up to 70% that is good
well yo good all right I sent you an
email from the test phone okay cool so
let's go back to obd2 Pitts we're gonna
want to send the request we're just
gonna deal with the main ECU for now but
it's interesting that those things do
respond Jessie the contractor who wrote
the panda elm software for us had some
pretty good comments about this stuff
let's see what you wrote so our stuff is
here that's actually the co knowledge
was in the safety it tells you what the
spec is it's actually being implemented
here yeah so this so the Honda uses
these really high up addresses check or
someone said if an address is 7 TF or
address and okay that's good to know
this is the Honda one
no open bottle does not have emergency
safety features it's not really to be
viewed at as a safety device we do think
that it makes driving safer but now it
doesn't oh oh it's been it's been it's
been updated by this one oh how much do
I have to pay for this okay so first off
it's a hundred thirty-eight I do believe
that Swiss francs okay let's get this
for free
well let's preview man ISO standards a
pricey an Apple lock meow lock me out of
watch you rich paying how many chips
look like I'm paying them any chips
mommy figures
Oh perform Broadway Val I'll have to buy
if I want that okay
who knows how I get free ISO things oh
did the Swedish make it available free
Swedish my girls like that
PewDiePie Swedish he's the most famous
youtuber ever oh yeah oh no it's a it's
a it's a Provo sings like example our
yeah Pirate Bay yeah for some reason I
don't think there's gonna be up on the
Pirate Bay okay alright let's just see
what we can find that's not I self and
so this is like yeah how to request you
game this is how I figured out how to do
that VIN request you know what we'll
just figure it off a little Kapiti pay
just can't be that hard
so these pigs are like the standard ones
they're used by like emissions people
see mode five just modify redo they come
in with the different modes of arson
where this motor mold want the
exceptions are PID one which is only
available in mode one and PID two which
is only available in mode tool oh here
we go show current data all right so
that's mode once
let me just try sending a100 and seeing
what happens so we're sending engine ECU
we're receiving it from the engine ECU I
just read that it's supposed to be +8
let's see what this does
well cool gives me some stuff okay so
this is allegedly the PIDs supported and
I believe it's bit encoded yeah it's
been encoded okay so let me just start
writing this standard quickly um very
poor dead PIDs then it looks like the
cons responds from MSB to LSB he's our
first aw I guess it starts with 1
because 0 pit is always supported and
that's what I'm sending ok so just make
a get PID D I should name the thing
correctly the mode 1 what didn't want
where did they use get get current now I
just say red equal get data for PID 0
that's the works I remove this extra
debug crap from here yeah you know I
don't really write in a Python 3
compatible way Python 3 is a disaster so
we can find out this getting bin doing
any more cool so those are my supported
pets
now it's MSB for
so what's the easiest way to do this
support it equals that I wanna do this
too strong and I should see anything
page 132 was the max you see below X 20
is the max 20 yeah y equals 1 to
infinity I mean you can do that if your
language is lazy I think your Friday
equals 1 to infinity I mean just wow I
plus 1 box if supported and 1 2 3
watch it watch oh I support it if left
equals y guy should standardize
something I shouldn't call one of them
query and one of them yeah let's did I
take that word query from somewhere I
try to make things as standard as
possible unsupported types for tuple and
Aunty add extract okay cool so those are
the supported pads for the car so we can
get calculated engine load we can get
long term fuel trims we can get intake
manifold pressure wait I can't get
engine rpm now that's weak I just made a
mistake trihex thumping get current-day
- my flat for PID 168 I'm just
data for PID let's try okay so 12 should
be the engine rpm seem like it says it's
not supported and yet stepper motor
designed to control car all question the
safety of those things uh but if you
have one I mean I'm not sure we can
really review it I mean I can look at it
like you posted on everything really the
way to do it is like posted on github
and yeah so you got you got to make sure
you do it safely so if you're gonna
build a external steering control you
need two things to be enforced by the
hardware practically you need a torque
limit and you need a disengagement
side so yeah I mean posted on the
Internet
we have a community going our slack and
see what you love to say okay so I
understand
oh that's the PID wait
mode 1 PID zero our quest for this PID
doesn't make sense
like I'm sure this car can fetch the RPM
between monitor idea supported okay
let's look at this mode thing happens if
Neo CPU fails um also they'll stop
sending messages to the car
so the dashboard will turn orange you'll
get the lights you'll get beeps well I
can request trouble codes with mode
three wow that's actually really easy
updo that only other easy use as well by
the way I'm watching the stream and it's
really laggy is it lagging for you too
well you're actually seeing up to the
minute what I'm doing like when I talk
I'm like I ran query van I ran query van
does that work no like okay it just
likes for me weird um that's why I
thought it was broken before
silky-smooth that's what I like to hear
okay so that's the engine rpm um let's
see community according to this can we
request the throttle position position
is 17 which isn't here either yeah I
know it works
weird did I write this code wrong all
maybe things aren't sent as MSB
you
each bit from MSB to LSB I did that
right seven eight nine oh oh oh
cuz this is that after after the big
endian here actually let me actually do
proper big endian like that ah much
better
okay that's a lot more sensible now can
I get things like the wattle position in
rpm yes I can 17 and 12 so let's make a
little loop here want extract the
current data for the pin so I know that
that's two bytes
untaek so this is your RPM and let's
also get what else can I guess throttle
position that's what I was gonna get and
the level three autonomous a know fully
fake news so you have to realize how a
lot of auto manufacturers view
self-driving they don't actually care
about it and they actually really don't
like it um because you know if you
believe all the predictions about
mobility as a service yeah yeah yeah
they sell less cars so they're doing
this the only reason they ship any of
this stuff is for press the Audi a8 the
l3 Audi a8 is a press stunt GM
supercruise is a press stunt right they
ship it on one Cadillac they're not
actually shipping it on their cars they
ship it on one Cadillac that car sells
five thousand cars a year it's a PR
stunt practically do I think
Ilan gta4 what
do I think Ilan zga for his drive across
the country is realistic maybe chess is
about six months to a year ahead of us
requires an argument for that number is
required
this is some like trick okay so this is
100 times 255 can you jailbreak your ps3
with your panda I wouldn't know anything
about that would I okay cool
let's see if it works let me get over
here into the driver's seat and now
let's press on the throttle and see if
it changes oh yeah look at that kayaking
with pandas bro car hacking with pandas
that's nice
oh you're starting up see if we get some
RPMs look at them RPMs I think I did the
math wrong I don't think that's the
right number of rpms
okay 256 times a closed B also I gonna
divide by four it says oh that was so
easy you guys bro so easy show you Oh
show you me stepping on the throttle
like that well you can see like the ref
count on a car and it matches what's on
the screen process called car hacking
all right it's turns off it's loud boom
boom okay cool um who knows what boost
is we were having a debate last night
about what boo sticks none of us really
knew and but none of us I mean I was
talking with our designer who's made
shiver look awesome by the way and he
didn't know a boost wasn't like really
Oh boosters either but I think no not
Boost Mobile no way yeah I mean boost
okay so let's see what else we can get
from these things
oh we can get the PID supported 20 as
well 20 gets you more pids for to get
you more PIDs okay so we'll have those
two might get supported pids function
all right
let's write this in a not crappy way but
you knowing me I will write in a crappy
way pit equals one rangy pit boss head
cast is through 21 plus pig pig pig and
range zero see how many goes work Pig
supported air
oh sweet it works all the way up let's
see easier although so we won't send a
zero alright alright does not work you
make typos oh it's on the car accessory
boats what we're all four here not the
normal mode data yeah so this is just
normal mode data yeah when I'm not
getting past any gateways right now
okay so it looks like it doesn't even
support the last request hey it says
that standard scam Oh unless that not
right no scam like time out okay so
these are all my supported pits see what
this Bwana Juanes woggs iller en put and
out push yeah I know I am
Toyota socks with standard peds that's
too bad well it says it supports 96 how
does that how is that possible that must
mean I made a mistake
oh I know oh that's clever
okay alright I understand now wild one
kid plus equals twenty if did not and
supported break variable pitter four
side Oh rats
alright yeah that makes us all right
let's do the trench sweet
so that returns all your supportive pits
and we'll add this code to pant I'll
kind of clean it up
totally off stream some lights on yeah
Toyota lights oh yo ice cream light this
up Joe that's a real life not like just
nothing at all John Dylan alright so
those are our supportive pads what do
you think what do you guys think the
coolest pads to display will be like by
default on shiver as I'm writing this
stuff now well I get the temperature of
the engine that's kind of cool
use your phone flash on your flappy
mirror thing wow that's bright it's too
bright can't do it what's the coolest
one of these fuel pressure see how do
you know how torque is getting yeah can
we get that so I don't see it here I'd
love to see fuel usage but yes a house
torque doing that I've seen that in
torque does that actually work or is it
just estimated because I don't see
anything here that would let you
actually get that rpm speed gear
consumption torque a transmission
battery voltage we're gonna get you guys
so that's actually I don't think on here
either
huh okay well that's interesting but no
go back to that later
um non-standard PIDs oh very limited
information Oh should reverse engineer
them and make it available for free cuz
I love free I love free yeah I think it
does math current current of what I can
get you current from the Panda pandas
have current and voltage sensors in them
um but okay yeah so that's the speeds a
good one to get vehicle speed km/h he
tells me the vehicle speed accurate to
literally one kilometer per hour week
I like accuracy you know you don't have
another bite
your phone's GPS you don't know but you
yes because that's you could they
couldn't afford another bite they
couldn't give me the speed two to two
bits of precision all right well this is
where we have open dvc
[Music]
so we'll move the query all ECU's things
somewhere else Kevin's kind of cool
shouldn't really send the PID if it's
not supported seven is fine let's rename
it MV queries in which we name it very
very thin stats that's cool this is a
code that's gonna go into Schiffer
obviously not the pipe shiver is no
longer written in Python it wasn't one
point but it's not anymore
so what else do we want speed revs
throttle battery voltage anymore see no
it's written in JavaScript huh the
futures JavaScript runtime since engine
start well that's interesting because we
should be able to query at least if the
engine is started with that
and watching we send this so in cars
with more it's in cars like the Honda
we're gonna have to use that one try to
comment there oh did open pilot zero
point three point seven just got pushed
it might have it might have been pushed
into Val I'm pretty cool stuff in there
no I'm not logged into anything here
let's check it out
open pal zero point three point seven
release check it out guys this one's
exciting yeah we have we have lots of
improved stuff yeah go to get up coming
I open pilot checks out but let's go
back to what I was doing
haha should work it's gonna update your
panda to the latest panda firmware - let
me just name this thing properly what's
happening right now so I'm setting some
standard queries to the car you can see
that I'm getting the speed the rpm and
the throttle right now
and I've managed to clear the supported
pids I'm also getting the VIN number
from the car actually want to be better
about this oops I should really write a
parser for this and I'll just do two :
but hey you know so what happens if I
Google this then that's good idea Toyota
rav4 and I'm gonna find out all the
terrible stuff that happened to my car
did I get a good price let's check let's
check to history melody Twitter's plus I
bought it from mmm look at this oh yeah
I think that's the price they're asking
I got a good price 34
you know I think car dealers is one of
those industries that like makes all
their money off like a few suckers
alright cool
that's what happens when you query then
that's a little crazy though that you
can just like query the van you like no
so where someone bought the car and
stuff oh mode 21 for Toyota the voltage
of the traction battery and a hybrid
electric vehicle that's exciting I
should probably ask for store DTC's as
well
Java's car has any make that Turkish
effort as well what does a dtc that's
not a did you say cool
yeah extended warranties i probably tell
scammy business all right
control model module voltage job
exciting no
so oven pilot won't update on reboot
we've only pushed to devel we haven't
pushed to release yet so if you are a
developer you can check it out if you're
not a developer you probably want to
wait till a few people check it out
first
i'm still visible it's good oxygen
sensors engine coolant temperature well
definitely check that one no it's called
temperature call him okay so I'll just
subtract 40 from this one PID 5 it's one
bite okay no now you're looking at this
no charge why you're a terrible code
okay well to clean up
I did write a really terrible code
truly atrocious well 39 degrees Celsius
it's that warm or cold
I don't know how Celsius has worked
sounds kind of warm though can't blow
water though are you cool mom one more
stat I need one more stat engine load
yeah it's probably pretty cool I support
that load yeah load no it's one of those
percent once does that really what took
away from that point zero to where you
want it I don't even have that many
degrees of significant figures
cool cool guys I'm pretty happy with
that
so we'll add ice OTP will add craving
stats what I do doing that I think I
need that get the gif well unless it's
vicinage change yeah yeah oh I did
change this yeah I added I added those
okay that's a cool
probably refactor eyes OTP to be
somewhere else but yeah we can be that
later can I make it honk well we'll do
that on the next session what do you all
think about that we'll try to do some
crazy stuff we're even and stats ok guys
I think that is live let me go to OBS
let's what my food is here I'd be real
happy if my food is here a shell cool I
just pick myself full screen here all
that's so pixelated let me just make it
less pixelated oh but now it did that
come on OBS why would anybody want to do
that wrong choice broski all right
thanks everyone for joining this
periscope and it's a little dark and
you'll try some white so let's turn some
lights on any last questions wait it's
hunk actually a code I really don't
think hunk is a code but if I'm wrong
and we can make the code hunk very
easily a car honk very easily I am sold
oh no I don't think that works what's
your question I'll try it next up I'll
tell you next time we learn for next
time next time I got a point to the
right place
how's vim but you gotta ask man just me
tonight I hope my foods inside who
thinks patrasche was inside uh yeah you
should have got an email you sure got an
email if your Panda has shipped
um which should be almost all the pandas
now are you sure got an email what's the
goal of what of the goal of this the
goal of this was just to get some cool
stats so those five stats that I just
wrote that Python to do we're gonna hand
off to the app team and they're gonna
add them to shiver
what is sync up and drive well know what
that is
sync up and dry let's go
thank you thing sync up and drive oh
it's like some t-mobile oh they make
like crappy dongle so I say why they all
make dongles this is like a new pivot
for the broski's the the phone carriers
phone Appetit alright alright cool guys
see y'all later thanks for joining wait
wait wait
post that again send 750 I'll do that
I'll do that what do we got
I'm counting on you 750 oh for
okay next time next time